

# **Marco Solazzi**

Nationality: Italian Date of birth: 01/10/1979

Email address: marco.solazzi@gmail.com

**Twitter:** <a href="https://twitter.com/dwightjack">https://twitter.com/dwightjack</a>

GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/dwightjack/">https://github.com/dwightjack/</a>

in LinkedIn: <a href="https://it.linkedin.com/in/marcosolazzi">https://it.linkedin.com/in/marcosolazzi</a>

**Website:** <a href="https://marco.solazzi.me">https://marco.solazzi.me</a>

• Home: Tokyo (Japan)

### **ABOUT ME**

I've been working in the web development field for almost 20 years and I've been spending the latest 10 years as a client-side frontend engineer.

I specialize in semantic UI development, web design systems, and accessibility. I am also interested in frontend developer experience (tooling and stack management). I love contributing to Open Source projects, and I strongly believe in the value of sharing knowledge to create growth opportunities for everyone.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# **Senior Frontend Engineer - Frontend Architect**

**Mercari Inc** [ 17/02/2020 – Current ]

City: Tokyo | Country: Japan | Website: <a href="https://www.mercari.com/jp/">https://www.mercari.com/jp/</a>

### Team

2020 ~ 2023/08 Merpay Frontend (~12 developers) (https://www.merpay.com/) 2023/08 ~ Merpay Client Architect (~6 developers) (https://www.merpay.com/)

### Mission

UX and UI Development, Software architecture.

### **Technical Activities**

- Development and maintenance of the company's internal and external client-side applications.
- Design and implementation of Merpay frontend accessibility strategy Improvement of the internal documentation and knowledge base
- Review and exploration of the technical stack
- Support and facilitation of product teams on CI-related tasks
- Management of the team's cross-project development tickets

# **Achievements**

- With the help of the team members, we were able to design and setup an automated accessibility audit to monitor each project's base accessibility.
- Constant UI library improvement and maintenance for internal dashboards, including DX and UX improvements.
- Management of the 2-year-long migration process from Nuxt 2 to Nuxt 3 of 7 internal and public applications.

# **Senior Frontend Developer, UX Engineer**

**Shiftbrain Inc** [ 16/01/2018 – 07/02/2020 ]

City: Tokyo | Country: Japan | Website: https://www.shiftbrain.com/

## **Company size**

~20 employees

#### **Team**

Frontend Development Team (6 developers)

#### Mission

UX and UI development of corporate design systems in collaboration with the Design Team.

### **Technical Activities**

- UX engineering: HTML (Pug), React/Vue.js, presentational JavaScript and CSS (Sass), accessibility.
- Frontend Ops: Design and development of the development toolchain (Webpack, Gulp, Storybook, Jest)

## **Company Activities**

- Promotion of agile development
- Styleguide-driven development evangelist

### **Achievements**

In collaboration with my team leader, we introduced a scrum-based and component-driven development workflow leveraging git-flow, code reviews, and isolated component development with Storybook and Jest.

### **Relevant Projects**

In early 2018 I was part of the restyle project for the Toyota corporate website.

In mid-2018, I was the leading developer in charge of the Soup Stock Tokyo corporate website design system. In mid-2019, I was tasked to develop the frontend code and WordPress theme of a media site for FujiTV.

# Senior Frontend Developer, UX Engineer

**AQuest S.r.l.** [ 01/12/2014 – 01/09/2017 ]

City: Verona | Country: Italy | Website: https://www.aquest.it/

## **Company size**

~80 employees

### **Team**

Frontend Development Team (6 developers)

### Mission

As a UX Engineer, I was in charge of the development and technical design of frontend interfaces and animations for corporate and marketing websites in collaboration with the design and backend team.

### **Technical Activities**

- UX/UI development: HTML (Nunjucks, ejs), React/Vue.js, ES6+ and CSS (Sass), accessibility
- Creative development: GSAP, Velocity
- Frontend Ops: Design and development of the team's internal tools for build and development (Webpack, Gulp, Gruntjs)
- Backend development: SSR solutions with Nodejs and IIS for React and Vue.js

# **Company Activities**

- Frontend best practices evangelist
- Styleguide-driven development evangelist
- Accessibility expert
- Tutoring and technical leadership for junior developers

### **Achievements**

I actively promoted development best practices such as Agile and cross-functional teams. I was one of the promoters and tutors of the introduction of git, git-flow, and GitLab as the primary workflow for both the frontend and backend development teams.

## **Relevant Projects**

From early 2016 to the end of 2017, I was part (as an interactive and design system developer) of the team tasked with designing and developing Mediaset Premium (the largest Italian private television network) corporate website and its smart TV/mobile application.

In 2017 I was in charge of the UX development of Carrefour Italy e-commerce platform and design system.

### **Awards**

- Awwwards Site of the Day: Fornasetti History (2015)
- Awwwards Site of the Day: Muller Italy (2016)
- Awwwards Site of the Day: Formigari (2017)

# Senior Frontend Developer, UX Engineer

*Intesys S.r.l.* [ 02/12/2009 – 30/11/2014 ]

City: Verona | Country: Italy | Website: http://www.intesys.it

# **Company size**

~100 employees

### Team

Digital and Tech Development Unit (~60 developers)

### Mission

Fullstack development and technical design for corporate websites, mobile web applications, and hybrid mobile applications (native+web).

Since 2011, my main focus has been frontend development and UX.

## **Technical Activities**

- Frontend development: HTML, CSS (Sass), JavaScript (jQuery, Angular.js, Backbone/Marionette, Sencha UI)
- Backend development: PHP (Zend, WordPress), database (MySQL, PostgreSQL)
- Frontend Ops: Frontend toolchain (Gruntis)

## **Company Activities**

- Frontend Advisory Group Leader
- WordPress Advisory Group Leader
- HR: frontend technical recruiter

### **Achievements**

Since 2011, my main focus has been defining and promoting the company's standards and best practices for frontend development. I've also been very active in introducing UX analysis for interface design.

## **Relevant Projects**

From 2010 to early 2012, I was actively involved in a team dedicated to developing and maintaining BMW Italy websites and web applications.

Between 2011 and 2012, I collaborated with the Mobile Development Unit to develop a social platform for Deutz-Fahr with both a web application and part of a mobile hybrid application.

## Freelance JavaScript Columnist

**HTML.it S.r.l.** [ 16/02/2009 – 30/11/2014 ]

City: Rona | Country: Italy | Website: <a href="http://www.html.it">http://www.html.it</a> | Business or sector: Information and communication

HTML.it is the leading resource for technical articles and guides in Italian.

#### Mission

Promotion of best practices and new technologies related to JavaScript.

## Main projects and achievements

As a technical writer, I curated the realization of the jQuery and jQuery UI guide.

# Frontend Web Developer / Full Stack Web Developer

**Promobit Communications S.r.l.** [ 04/07/2005 – 29/11/2009 ]

City: Verona | Country: Italy | Website: http://www.promobit.com/

## **Company size**

~15 employees

#### Team

Design and Development Team (3 developers/designers)

### Mission

I was head of the development team on various web marketing projects as well as the maintainer of the IT infrastructure

## **Technical Activities**

- Frontend development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript (jQuery, Mootools)
- Backend development: PHP (Joomla, WordPress, Codelgniter), MySQL
- IT: Web servers (CentOS), SVN server, System Administrator

### **Company Activities**

- Project management
- Technical recruitment

### **Achievements**

I was able to manage multiple web portals introducing a standardized template system based on the Joomla! CMS and a scrum-based development cycle to mitigate tight deadlines.

# **Relevant Projects**

Given the limited amount of data right now it doesn't seem like a big deal, but being able to manage and keep safe a web server, an SVN server, and a ticketing / CRM system with customers' data was a big challenge at that time.

### **EDUCATION AND TRAINING**

# **Web Developer and Designer**

Unionservices (Confcommercio Verona) [ 10/2004 – 04/2005 ]

City: Verona | Country: Italy | NQF Level: Diploma regionale

- Web Design
- Web Marketing
- Macromedia Studio (Flash, Dreamweaver, Freehand)
- Adobe Photoshop Image Ready

### **Cisco Certified Network Associated**

**Cisco Networking Academy** [ 01/10/2003 – 01/06/2004 ]

City: Verona | Country: Italy

- WAN and LAN Networking
- Network Design and administration
- Cisco Routers configuration and administration

# **Bachelor's Degree in Communication Sciences**

University of Modena and Reggio Emilia [ 12/1998 – 06/2003 ]

City: Reggio Emilia | Country: Italy | Level in EQF: EQF level 6

- · Mass Media
- Internet Technologies
- Social Sciences
- Semiotics

## **JOB-RELATED SKILLS**

### **Technical Skills**

Languages: HTML5, CSS3, Sass/SCSS, ES2015+, TypeScript, PHP7

Frontend Libraries and Frameworks: Vue.js, Nuxt, React, Svelte, Astro, Tailwind CSS, GSAP, Angular + RXJS

Developer Experience: Jest, Cypress, Playwright, Vitest, Mocha + Chai, ESLint, stylelint, Storybook

Build Tools: Vite, webpack, Rollup, esbuild, Turborepo, gulp

# Job-related skills

I have good knowledge of UX principles related to web design and web development. I'm particularly interested in UI development and micro-interaction design as the key to better user experience.

I promote accessibility best practices to create a better web for everyone.

## **LANGUAGE SKILLS**

Mother tongue(s): Italian

Other language(s):

**English** French

LISTENING C1 READING C1 WRITING B2 LISTENING B1 READING B1 WRITING A2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION B2 SPOKEN INTERACTION C1 SPOKEN PRODUCTION A2 SPOKEN INTERACTION A2

### Japanese

LISTENING B1 READING A1 WRITING A2

**SPOKEN PRODUCTION B1 SPOKEN INTERACTION B1** 

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

### **ORGANISATIONAL SKILLS**

**Organisational skills** I am an active promoter of agile development and cross-functional teams. As a UX Engineer, I am confident I can sit between the design and development teams to promote cross-team communication and shared knowledge.

Since 2021, I have managed frontend shared tasks, coordinating maintenance, security updates, and performance improvements between different product teams in a fast-paced environment.

From 2014 to 2022, I co-founded my hometown's local frontend meetup (FEVR http://www.fevr.it/), promoting knowledge sharing around the best and newest frontend technologies.

From 2015 to 2018, we co-organized the main international conference in Italy about React (<a href="https://www.reactisday.it">https://www.reactisday.it</a>). My main tasks were selecting speeches and co-hosting the event.

## **COMMUNICATION AND INTERPERSONAL SKILLS**

**Communication and interpersonal skills** Through the years, I gained confidence in public speaking, participating both as a speaker and as a host of local meetups and conferences.

## **Speeches**

## **Tools and Strategies for Frontend UI Libraries**

Event: Merpay Tech Fest 2022

Slides: https://speakerdeck.com/mercari/tools-and-strategies-for-frontend-ui-libraries

Video: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3NbvlpE\_2a0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3NbvlpE\_2a0</a>

# **Automation Strategies for Baseline Accessibility**

Event: Merpay Frontend Tech Talk

Slides: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/automation-strategies-for-baseline-accessibility-merpay-tech-talk-2021">https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/automation-strategies-for-baseline-accessibility-merpay-tech-talk-2021</a>

Video: <a href="https://youtu.be/g">https://youtu.be/g</a> ncv-| IGA?t=2278

# **Historiae JavaScript**

Event: local meetup, October 2016

Slides: https://speakerdeck.com/fevr/historiae-javascript

# Accessibility tips & tricks for CSS developers

Event: CSS Day IT, March 2016

Slides: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/accessibility-tips-and-tricks-for-css-developers">https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/accessibility-tips-and-tricks-for-css-developers</a>

Video (IT): <a href="https://vimeo.com/165114097">https://vimeo.com/165114097</a>

## **Lean Front-end Development**

Event: Codemotion Milan, November 2015

Slides: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/fevr/lean-frontend-development-at-codemotion-milano-2015">https://speakerdeck.com/fevr/lean-frontend-development-at-codemotion-milano-2015</a>

# CSS workflow for grown-ups

Event: CSS Day IT, March 2015

Slides: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/css-workflow-for-grown-ups">https://speakerdeck.com/dwightjack/css-workflow-for-grown-ups</a>

Video (IT): https://vimeo.com/127662618